Luther E. Grim and Dorothy H. Grim map collection
Geography and Map Division, Library of Congress
Luther E. Grim and Dorothy H. Grim map collection 1942-1964
G3701.A5 coll .G7 Grim
Grim, Luther, E., 1914-1964
33 items
32 maps
1 textual document
Geography and Map Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
The collection consists of 32 pictorial, tourtist, and road maps published between 1942 and 1964. The materials depict the moon and various locations in the United States. Several of these maps were designed for classroom instruction. Publishers include Armour and Company, General Drafting Company, Esso Standard Oil Company, among others. Included is an envelope from the Armour and Company addressed to Mrs. Dorothy H. Grim, N. Hopewell-Winterstown Elementary School, Red Lion, Pa. Mrs. Grim taught the fifth grade and used the materials in her classroom. Luther E. Grim was her husband.
Provenance
Luther E Grim and Dorothy H. Grim were the parents of Geography and Map Division specialist Ronald E. Grim. The materials were donated to the division in 1986.
Access and Restrictions
The Luther E. Grim and Dorothy H. Grim map collection collection is open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Geography and Map Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Luther E. Grim was born in 1914 and died in 1964. He is buried in York County, Pennsylvania.
Dorothy H. Grim was born in 1917 and died in 1996. She was a teacher of the fifth grade at North Hopewell-Winterstown Elementary School in Red Lion, PA. She obtained the maps for her classroom by writing to publishers.
Scope and Content Note
The collection consists of 32 pictorial, tourtist, and road maps published between 1942 and 1964. The materials depict the moon and various locations within the United States. Several of these maps were designed for classroom instruction. Publishers include Armour and Company, General Drafting Company, Esso Standard Oil Company, among others.
Arrangement
The Luther E. Grim and Dorothy H. Grim map collection collection is organized in a single series:
Series I Luther E. Grim and Dorothy H. Grim map collection
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Grim, Dorothy H. 1917-1996; Grim, Luther E., 1914-1964, compiler.
Organizations
Armour and Company. Department of Food Economics; Esso Standard Oil Company; General Drafting Company
Subjects
Roads--United States--Maps.
Places
Moon--Maps.; United States--Maps.
Form/Genre
Instructional and educational works.; Maps.; Pictorial maps.; Road maps.
Container List
- Luther E. Grim and Dorothy H. Grim map collection
  - A Guide to the Stars: Scientific Chart of the Galaxy Showing Principal Stars and Constellations, Signs of the Zodiac, the nine planets of the solar system and other astronomical wonders, 1951, 1; 36 x 48 cm
    Robert R. Coles, Hayden Planetarium.
    James Gordon Irving, Illustrator.
    Amoco Oil Guide.
    Verso: Constellations of spring, summer, autumn and winter.
  - My Weekly Reader Map of the Moon, 2; 97 x 64 cm
    C.S Hammond and Co.
  - Map of the Moon, Esso, 1969, 3; 47 x 61 cm
    Esso Standard Oil Company.
    Hammond Incorporated.
    Includes place names and text.
    Relief shown by shading.
    Date estimated.
  - Trip to the Moon, Esso, 1969, 4; 47 x 61 cm
    With 9 inset views of various stages of the trip to the Moon, photographed by NASA.
  - A Two-Way Street Between the Americas, 1949, 5; 102 x 67 cm
    Pan-American Coffee Bureau.
    "Coffee... Is the major commodity in the Inter-American trade."
    Pictorial map.
  - Oil in America: A pictorial story of the Petroleum Industry in the United States, 1957, 6; 85 x 61 cm
    General Drafting Company.
    Standard Oil Company.
    Pictorial depictions of oil uses for each state.
    Three inset maps at top showing producing states, pipelines, and refineries.
    The verso has text on the contributions of the oil industry to the American economy and standard of living.
  - Armour Food Source Map, 1960, 7; 62 x 94 cm
    Armour & Company.
    "The greatness of the United States is founded on Agriculture."
    Bottom left: "This map shows you where various foods are produced in quantities large enough to supply other regions as well as local needs."
    Verso: History of the American Food Industry.
    With text and photographs.
  - Map of the United States (Geographically Correct) Issued by Union Pacific Railroad, 1959, 8; 48 x 79 cm
    Rand McNally, Chicago.
  - Great Northern Railway Map of the United States, 1952, 9; 46 x 81 cm
    McGill-Warner Co.
    1:6,336,000.
    Three maps on one sheet. Main map shows the route of the Great Northern Railway, Burlington Lines, Main Connection, other railroads, and steamship lines into US ports. The two inset maps show Great Northern Railway and steamship lines to Asia, and steamship line connections to Alaska.
  - Indiana Toll Road "Main Street of the Midwest", 1965, 10; 23 x 82 cm
    Indiana Toll Road Commission.
    1:2,000,000.
    Shows turnpikes in eastern states connecting with Indiana Toll Road.
    Includes information and toll road indexes.
    Verso: three maps. Linkin the East and West: The Indiana Toll Road, Turnpike Routes to the New York World's Fair, and World's Fair and Vicinity.
  - Forest and Trees of the United States, 11
    American Forest Industries.
    Shows forests in the United States.
    Drawings of various tree types surround map.
  - Folkore and Legends of Our Country, 1960, 12; 61 x 89 cm
    Soltesz.
    Esso Standard Oil Compnay.
    Map includes insets of Alaska and Hawaii. Relief shown by shading.
    Verso: pictorial road map of Atlantic and Gulf states with selected points of interest, descriptive list with additional points of interest.
    Includes text: "Treasuries of Americana" and "Produced for teacher's classroom use."
  - Life in Colonial America and The Westward Expansion of the United States, 1958, 13; 85 x 67 cm
    Map of life in colonial Americas, shows state boundaries, historical notes, views of colonial life and settlements.
    Map of the westward expansion of the United states showing historical territories, major cities, table of states and their population, text panels, etc.
  - Westward Across the Map: In the Americas, 1962, 14
    Hanna, Kohn, and Lively.
    The Basic Social Studies Program: Scott, Foresman and Company.
    Stars in Our Flag.
  - Western Wonderlands: Served by the Union Pacific Railroad, 1958, 15; 46 x 60 cm
    Recto: color brochure.
    Verso: pictorial map "The Union Pacific West".
  - Ohio Turnpike Map-Folder, 1965-1966 Edition, 1965, 16; 46 x 46 cm
    Ohio Turnpike Commission.
    Includes mileage table and toll schedule for the Ohio Turnpike.
    Verso: "Ohio Points of Interest".
  - Historic Trails Through New Mexico the Land of Enchantment, 1951, 17; 55 x 43 cm
    New Mexico State Tourist Bureau.
    Wilfred Stedman.
    Pictorial map howing explorer routes, old trails, illustrations of explorers, animals, army posts, pueblos, state and national monuments, drainage, and other popular places of interest.
    Verso: information about explorers and trails.
  - Illinois Tollway and Connecting Highways Showing all the Entrances and Exits, 1958, 18; 69 x 36 cm
    Illinois State Toll Highway Commission.
    Indicates all speed regulations/limits at the time for cars, buses, and trucks.
  - Hawaiian Airlines Map of the State of Hawaii, circa 1960, 19; 41 x 28 cm
    Verso: See all of Hawaii Island State of Enchantment.
  - Route Map Hawaiian Airlines: See all Hawaii, circa 1953, 20; 25 x 52 cm
    Hawaiian Airlines.
    Pictorial map of Hawaiian Islands.
    Includes mileage chart.
  - Island of Oahu State of Hawaii, 21
    Going Places See Things by the Gray Line.
    Tourist map.
  - Pearl Harbor a Daily Cruise to Pearl Harbor is made by the Motor Yacht "Adventure", 22
    Trips operated daily by Hawaiian Cruises, Ltd. Reservations through any travel agent.
    Brochure.
  - Places of Interest in Hershey, Pennsylvania - "The Chocolate Town", 23
    Hersey Park brochure and map.
  - Longwood Gardens Kennett Square, Pennsylvania: Guide Maps to the Conservatories and Outdoor Gardens, 1964, 24
    Longwood Gardens brochure and map.
  - Pennsylvania the Keystone State, 25
  - [Old Quebec Its Accommodation and Best Shopping], 26
    Compliments of Motel l'Abitation.
  - Pilgrim's Map of the Holyland, 1942, 27; 20 x 28 cm
    Th. F. Mathesy, Ph. D.
  - Pilgrim's Map of the Holyland for Bible Research and Study, 28
  - United States Paste-up Map for Boys and Girls, 1949, 29; 20 x 28 cm
    The York Bank and Trust Company.
  - A Line on Maps: Map Study Kit, 1959, 30
    Esso Standard.
  - Rand McNally World Atlas Completely up to date full color maps for a better understanding of today's world: Compliments of Waldorf/Family Scott Bathroom Tissue, 1958, 31; 20 x 28 cm
    Rand McNally.
  - Texaco 49 - State Plus Canada - Hawaii Road Atlas, 1959, 32
    Texaco, Inc.